Welcome back to Apush in under three
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, we talked about all the
military stuff of the Civil War. Now,
let's examine the political side. At
first, Lincoln made it clear this war
was about preserving the Union, not
ending slavery. But, as the war dragged
on, that changed. Let's talk about how.
By 1862, Lincoln knew the war needed a
new purpose. And after the Union's sort
of victory at Antietam, he issued the
Emancipation Proclamation. This document
freed enslaved people in
Confederate-held territories, but not to
in border states. It reframed the war as
a fight against slavery, not just Union
preservation. And third, it kept Europe,
especially Britain and France, from
recognizing the Confederacy. Now, even
though it didn't immediately free all
enslaved people, it was a game-changer
because now thousands of formally
enslaved people escaped plantations and
enlisted in the Union Army. By the end
of this war, nearly 200,000
African-Americans fought for the Union.
The 1st South Carolina Volunteer
Infantry Regiment and the 54th
Massachusetts proved black soldiers were
essential to the Union victory. After
the bloodbath at Gettysburg, Lincoln
gave a two-minute speech that completely
redefined the Civil War. In it, he said,
number one, the war was about preserving
democracy and fulfilling the ideals of
the Founding Fathers. And number two,
the Union must win so government of the
people, by the people, for the people
shall not perish from the earth. This
speech solidified that America wasn't
just fighting the South, it was fighting
for its identity. But, I want you to
think beyond the political aspect for a
second. For black Americans all around
the country, this wasn't about some
simple politics. This is about having
the simple human right to live freely.
This is about being able to be treated
with just some dignity in their life.
This war was about freedom, democracy,
and most of all, national unity. On the
screen now are questions for this topic.
Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.